Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is צדי ו' *tzadi-vav*,
97, and we, that's a factor of two, right?
No, I'm sorry, it's divisible by two, it's not factors. Anyway, so
we pick up at the bottom of צדי ה' *tzadi-hei* of 95,
and we're in the middle of these stories about חזקיהו Chizkiyahu *Chizkiyahu*
and סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv* and the wiping out of the army of
סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv*, and how did the angel wipe out the armies
of סנחריב Sancheriv, *Sancheriv*, and how many people were left? And it
says, you know, just five,
נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar *Nevuchadnezzar*, נבוזראדן Nevuzaradan *Nevuzaradan*, who were ultimately like obviously like
still the seeds of the final destruction were still there even though
they were saved from this one, and סנחריב Sanheriv *Sancheriv* and his
two sons, and then his two sons murdered him when he went
back and was prostrating himself in his God's temple. So that's where
we left off. And now we are four lines from the bottom
on צדי ה' עמוד ב' *tzadi-hei amud bet*. אמר Amar רבי אבהו
*Amar Rabbi Abahu*, אלמלא מקרא כתוב אי אפשר לאומרו *ilmalei mikra katuv
iy efshar le'omro*, if it were not that it was a written
verse, it would be like heretical to say the following thing. דכתיב
d'chsiv, *Dichitiv*, what does the verse say? ביום ההוא יגלח ה' בתער
השכירה *bayom hahu yigalach Hashem betaar hasechira*, that day God will give
a shave, will shave with the rented razor, בעברי נהר *be'evrei nahar*,
in the passing over of the river, במלך אשור *bimelech Ashur*, the
king of Assyria, את הראש ושיער הרגליים *et harosh vese'ar haraglayim*, the
head and the hair of the legs, וגם את הזקן תספה vegam
et hazakan tispeh. *vegam et hazakan tispeh*, and even the beard he
will destroy. So God is going to give סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv* a
shave. Okay, so what does that mean? Like God will use this
razor to give, to shave off the hair of
סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv*? So
אתא קודשא בריך הוא *ata Kudsha Brich Hu*, God came and ואידמי
ליה כגברא סבא *ve'idmi lei k'gavra saba*, and
appeared to
סנחריב Sancheriv, *Sancheriv* like an old man. All right, so אמר ליה
Amar leih, *amar lei*, and said to him, כי אזלת לגבי מלכי
מזרח ומערב *ki azlat legabei malchei mizrach umaarav*,
you're now running back and returning to Assyria, you're going to come
to all of the kings of the east and the west, דאייתיתינהו
לבנייהו *de'aititinhu livnaihu*, you brought their children, remember before we said he
had whatever he had, 45,000 princes coming with him, so you had
all these armies accompanying you, all the princes of all of the
other nations, now you brought their children וקטלתינהו *vekataltinhu*, and you got
them all killed, מאי אמרת להו *mai amrat lehu*, what are you
going to say to them? They're going to say where are our
children?
סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv* said back to this person, God who was, you
know, somehow some image, you know, some way God was appearing to
him, anyway, appeared like this old man and said, אמר להו Amar
lehu, *amar lehu*, ההוא גברא hahu gavra, בההוא פחדא נמי יתיב *hahu
gavra bahu pachta nami yasiv*, so סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv* said back to
this person, you know what, that person, meaning I, that's exactly what
I'm afraid of. So אמר ליה Amar leih, *amar lei*, so
סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv* said to the old man, היכי נעביד *heichi naavid*,
so what should I do? אמר ליה Amar lei, *amar lei*, זיל
ושני נפשך *zil veshani nafshech*, go make yourself look different, go disguise
yourself. Top of צדי ו' עמוד א' *tzadi-vav amud alef*. במאי אשני
*b'mai eshani*, how can I disguise myself? אמר amar, ליה *amar lei*,
זיל אייתי Aiti, לי מספרא *zil aiti li mispara*, go get me
a scissors or a razor, how they translate that, razor or scissors,
scissors probably, right? Scissors, go get me a scissors ואיגזך *ve'egzach*,
and I'll give you a haircut. Okay, so
I don't know how a haircut totally changes your appearance, but maybe
if you also shave off the facial hair. אנא מהיכא אייתי *ana
meheicha aiti*, where can I get a scissors from? אמר amar, ליה
*amar lei*, עול להאי ביתא *oila l'hai baita*, go to that house
over there ואייתי *v'aiti*, and you'll bring what? אזל *azal*, he went,
אשכחינהו מלאכי השרת *ashkechinhu malachei hasharet*, so the heavenly angels found that
סנחריב Sancheriv *Sancheriv* was going to that house to get some scissors,
so ואידמי ליה כגברא *ve'idmi lei k'gavra*, they appeared to him, God's
appearing like an old man, they're appearing like men, God is a
man, I have no idea what to make of it, let's finish
the story. God appeared to them like an old man, they just
appeared to them like men, הוו קא טחני כשישא *havei katachni kashisa*,
and they went to the house and they were grinding *kashisa*. Palm
kernels, okay.
אמר amar, ליה *amar lei*, הבו לי מספרא *havu li
mispara*, so
סנחריב *Sancheriv* came and said, can you please give me a scissors?
I need to borrow scissors. אמר ליה *amar lei*, טחון חד גריוא
דכשישא וניתן לך *tchon chad giyura dekashisa u'niten lach*, you know what,
if you come and help us do grind a little unit of
these seeds, then we'll give it to you, you know, if you
want a scissors, you've got to work for it. טחן חד גריוא
דכשישא ויהבו ליה מספרתא *tchan chad giyura dekashisa v'yahu lei misparta*, of
course this is all very, you know, like the, I don't know
what the bigger point is, I have to admit I did not
have a chance to look at the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha*, but you
know, but obviously the point is that this is embarrassing to סנחריב
*Sancheriv*, I mean it's like it's completely, you know, demeaning to him.
But anyway, so, it also in my mind evokes a little bit
the whole, what do you call it, the whole Samson, you know,
where he's blinded and attached to this millstone. I but I really
don't know what to make of it. So טחון חד גריוא דכשישא
וניתן לך *tchon chad giyura dekashisa u'niten lach*, טחן חד גריוא דכשישא
ויהבו ליה מספרתא *tchan chad giyura dekashisa v'yahu lei misparta*, he ground
a unit of these seeds and they gave him a scissors. עד
דאתא *ad d'ata*, as it, while he was finally coming back to
the old man, God. Okay, איחשך, it took a long time so
it was growing dark, so אמר ליה, of course the funny thing
is, right, if he wanted to disguise himself, then just go, you
know, and don't return to your land and try to re-reassume the
kingship, right? You know, like, I mean, go run off to one
of these other countries or something like that. It's a little funny,
like what's he expecting to do? Go back and be king but
I'm going to look different and therefore they won't recognize me? Anyway,
whatever. Anyway, so it got dark. אמר ליה, זיל אייתי נורא, zil
aytei nura, so God said, I can't give you a haircut now,
it's too dark. Go bring me a fire. So אזל ואייתי נורא,
azal ve'aytei nura, so he went and he found somewhere to get
a fire. בהדי דקנפח ליה, Bahadei dekanafach leih, איתלי ביה נורא בדיקניה.
itli beih nura bedikneih.
As he was like blowing on the fire, I guess to keep
it going or something, the it caught you know his beard caught
fire from this candle or lantern he was bringing back. אזל גזייה
לרישיה ודיקניה. Azal gazyah lereisheih vedikneih.
So he went and he shaved off—did he shave off or God
shave off? The thing gets says then anyway it seems like it
says he
shaves off. Anyway anyway his hair and his and his beard so
his whole face shouldn't catch fire. So instead of God doing it
like I guess he did for himself.
So אמרו, Amru, so היינו דכתיב, hainu dechtiv, that's what's meant, וגם
את הזקן תספה. The beard will be destroyed, it doesn't say will
be shaved because that was destroyed by the fire. אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Papa, רב פפא Rav Papa says, היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu
de'amri inshi, that's why people
say
גרירתא
לארמאה gerirta l'arma'ah
שפיר ליה. shapir leih. If you, whatever, if you singe an Aramean,
it'll be good for him. איתלי ליה נורא בדיקניה, itli leih nura
bedikneih, and if you actually manage to get his beard caught on
fire, ולא שחך חוכא מיניה, velo shachach chucha mineih, he'll be so
happy his smile won't stop from him, he'll be so grateful for
you for having burned off his beard. So I don't understand what
this is doing from the beginning to the end. Michael, did you
see anything in the מהרש"א right there? All right. So anyway, here
this could be your homework assignment: make sense of how this is—of
what the meaning of any of this little story is. I do
not know. Okay, moving on. אמר—okay, אזל אשכח דפא. azal ashchach dapa.
So now Sancheirev is back on his way, we're end with God
giving Sancheirev a haircut. So Sancheirev is back on his way back
to Assyria and
he found a board מתיבותא דנח. miteivuta deNoach. Look, it's relevant to
this week's פרשה. parshah. He found a board from the from the
ark of Noah. אמר היינו אלהא רבא דשיזביה לנח מטופנא. Amar hainu
elaha raba deshizbeih leNoach mitufna. Oh, I now realize I was you
know fighting against the great God that saved Noah from the from
the flood. So it's a little funny, like now he realizes what's
going on here. You know, it's actually interesting because we all know
that these all of these nations have these flood narratives, right? These
flood narratives are very common in myths of ancient nations. So maybe
somehow that's what it's tapping into, like now he's sort of recognizing
you know somehow ultimately oh it's the God of the Israelites that
ultimately is the God behind these flood—but it's a little bit unclear
like how does he because he sees Noah's ark connect it you
know to God, our God, and how does he realize something he
didn't realize before? So I don't get this either. Anyway, אמר אי
אזילנא והוא גברא ומצלח, Amar ei azilna vehu gavra umatzlach, maybe he
meant the God who just gave me a haircut is the one—anyway
I don't know what to make of anyway this. Okay. Then he
said, אי אזילנא והוא גברא ומצלח, ei azilna vehu gavra umatzlach, you
know what? If I get to return back to my country and
I'm successful—because he's afraid of what's going to happen now that he
returns—so מקרבנא להו לתרין בנוהי קמך, mekarvna lehu letrin benohi kaimach,
I will offer my two sons as sacrifices to you. Again, like
why is that relevant? Like Noah came off of the ark and
offered sacrifices and there were two of each animal, I don't know,
like I mean, well if he had two sons like I'm not
getting this at all, I'm sorry to say.
Anyway, שמעו בנוהי וקטלוהו. shamu benohi vekatluhu. Ultimately this is to give
the backstory of what we read in the פסוקים, pesukim, which is
that when he was bowing down in the house of his god,
his sons killed him. Now why was he bowing down in the
house of his god if he's recognizing you know that he's going
to offer sons to our God? Anyway,
היינו דכתיב ויהי הוא משתחוה בית נסרך אלהיו ואדרמלך ושרהצר בנוהי הכהו
בחרב, hainu dechtiv vayehi hu mishtachaveh beit nisroch elohav veAdrammech veSharezer benohi
hikuhu bacharev, fine. All right, so that was the backstory, go figure
out what all of that meant. Okay, now since we mentioned the
angel that smote the Assyrian troops and we mentioned that the number
of troops that he brought with him is similar to the troops
that Abraham fought off and they're similar to the troops of גוג
ומגוג Gog uMagog where and I mentioned the whole issue about like
the cyclical nature of history of Jewish history and so on, what's
happened has already happened in the past, it'll happen in the future,
all sorts of you know strengthens the idea that this will be
ultimately you know what we're talking about, Messianic period and you know
wars of גוג ומגוג. Gog uMagog. Anyway, so now we look back
to the story of אברהם, Avraham, which is also a story of
him fighting you know these kings and with an according to the
מדרש, Midrash, it's going to be similarly an angel is going to
be... involved in it. So let's take a look. Look,
ויחלק עליהם לילה. Vayechalek Aleihem Layla. So the night divided on them
when he was chasing after these kings. So presumably what that means,
what does it mean the night divided on them? So presumably what
it means is like he divided his troops in the middle of
the night, he split up his troops or something. But let's see
what it says.
הוא ועבדיו Hu va-avadav he and his servants, ויכם vayakeim and they
smote them. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so look at this,
it's this week's פרשה parsha and next week's פרשה. parsha. אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, אותו מלאך שנתזמן לו לאברהם oto malach shenizdamen
lo le-Avraham the angel there, there was an angel that helped אברהם
Avraham like by the סנחריב story, לילה שמו Layla shemo and his
name was לילה. Layla. So ויחלק עליהם לילה Vayechalek Aleihem Layla means
the angel whose name is night divided for them like in a
common whatever assisted אברהם Avraham in his pursuing these troops.
He also got divided.
Right, yeah, neither do I. שנאמר Shene'emar והלילה אמר הורה גבר. ve-ha-layla
amar hora gaver. So here we have a,
לילה Layla is anthropomorphized. Night says a man has been conceived. But
because in this פסוק pasuk night is sort of, you know, anthropomorphized,
we're saying that night represents the name of an angel. רבי יצחק
נפחא אמר Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha amar no, שעשה עמו מעשה לילה, she-asah
imo ma'aseh layla, connecting it to another previous, another story, that what
it means the לילה Layla divided on them, it means was that
the night sort of fought against these kings, the same way we
see in the, in another story that elements of the night are
fighting against the king that's coming to war against Israel. What's that
other story? שנאמר Shene'emar מן השמים נלחמו הכוכבים ממסילותם Min ha-shamayim nilchamu
ha-kochavim mi-mesilotam from the heavens the, for from סיסרא, Sisra, right? From
the heavens the stars came and fought from their very, you know,
what's it called? Their from their paths in the sky, נלחמו עם
סיסרא. nilchamu im Sisra. Okay. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, there's
also Pharaoh going through the sea.
Where was there night there?
Isn't that at night they go through the sea?
No, the night there, they ולא קרב זה אל זה כל הלילה.
velo karav zeh el zeh kol ha-layla. They didn't approach at night,
and then in the morning, I guess they, you know, they died.
And then in morning they found them.
Oh, they found them, so that's where they were sort of pursued
towards the end of the night. That's true. Okay.
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, טבא דנפחא מדבר נפחא. tava de-Nafcha
mi-bar Nafcha. Oh, נפחא's Nafcha's explanation of רבי יצחק נפחא's Rabbi Yitzchak
Nafcha's explanation is better than בר נפחא. bar Nafcha. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is called בר נפחא. bar Nafcha. רש"י Rashi says maybe his
father's name was נפחא, Nafcha, maybe give an explanation. Oh, I like
this second explanation better than the first one, that it's not some
angel that's called night, but it means the stars of the night
or whatever came to fight. Okay. Now continuing with the story of
אברהם, Avraham, וירדוף עד דן Vayirdof ad Dan and he chased them
until דן, Dan, right, in the north of Israel.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כיון שבא אותו צדיק עד דן,
keivan sheba oto tzaddik ad Dan, תשיש כוחו. tashish kocho. His strength
ebbed and he wasn't able to continue pursuing them. Why? ראה בני
בניו שעתידין לעבוד עבודה זרה בדן. Ra'ah benei banav she-atidin la'avod avodah
zarah be-Dan. So we keep on sort of, you know, pointing backwards
and forwards into Jewish history, right? The סנחריב story points back to
אברהם, Avraham, the אברהם Avraham story but also you have by the
אברהם Avraham story it connects to the whole story about סיסרא Sisra
and דבורה, Devorah, etc. So here also אברהם Avraham was held back
by a future sin, that you know, in the end they would
have one of the golden calves, they would have, you know, that
they worshipped in the Israelite kingdom, they would have it in דן.
Dan. Right, so all of Jewish history is interconnected. שנאמר וישם את
האחד בבית אל ואת האחד נתן בדן Shene'emar vayaseim et ha-echad be-Veit
El ve-et ha-echad natan be-Dan one of the golden calves they put
in בית אל Beit El and one in דן. Dan. ואף אותו
רשע לא נתגבר עד שהגיע לדן. Ve-af oto rasha lo nitgaber ad
she-higia le-Dan.
Even that wicked person Nevuchadnezzar when he came to actually now we're
pointing going, you know, it's all connected, all these battles, right? So
now when Nevuchadnezzar is coming to destroy after the whole story about
about סנחריב, he also, he gains his strength when he approaches דן,
Dan, because he's coming to punish Israel, whatever, to afflict Israel. שנאמר
מדן נשמע נחרת סוסיו Shene'emar mi-Dan nishma nachrat susav from דן Dan
can be heard the whining, not whining, what do horses do? Whinnying
of the snorting of the, snorting of the snorting of the horses.
אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, אף על גב דשלח רבי, af
al gav de-shalach Rabbi, either רבי יהודה בן בתירה מנציבין Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira mi-Nitzivin or some say רבי יהושע בן לקיש. Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Lakish. Okay, even though רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua sent the or
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda sent the following message: הזהרו בזקן ששכח תלמודו.
hizaheru be-zaken she-shachach talmudo. Be careful
with an old person, an old scholar who, you know, sometimes out
of age people's memory go and he forgot his learning מחמת אונסו
machamat onso and due to no fault of his own, he just
grew old. So you know, you need to show continue to show
him great respect. והזהרו בורידין Ve-hizaheru bi-veridin as רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
This seems a very strange thing to put in the mix. And
when you slaughter a chicken or a fowl, make sure to cut
the carotid artery. רש"י Rashi says because sometimes you roast a bird
whole, so normally when you slaughter a cow you chop it up
into chunks of meat and you salt the individual pieces of meat
so you get out the blood. But when you slaughter a chicken
if you're going to roast it whole, the blood won't be able
to get out well enough. So what you need to do is
make sure you cut the carotid artery. That's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's
position. והזהרו בבני עמי הארץ Ve-hizaheru bi-venei amei ha-aretz and be careful
with the students of the commoners, you know, or of the farmers
or of their, the children, excuse me, the children, שמהן תצא תורה
she-mehen tetzei Torah from them תורה Torah will emerge. So even though
he said that, כי הא מילתא מודינא להו. ki ha milta modina
le-hu. This thing you tell them, huh? Even though he said that,
you tell them this thing. the connection.
So what he said before, is this a new thing?
Yeah, this seems to be a new thing. So what what the
heck is going on here? Okay, so the thing, so what we're
about to do, you know what, so let's do this. Let's put
that aside for a moment and see what the next passage of
the גמרא Gemara is, because he seems to be tying it into
the next passage of the גמרא, Gemara, and then we'll go back
and we'll unpack what that statement is, okay? And then we'll understand
why this is being brought. It's really being brought because of this
next passage of the גמרא. Gemara. So let's see what this thing
is. צדיק אתה ה' כי אריב אליך, Tzadik atah Hashem ki ariv
eilecha, God, you are righteous even when I sort of, you know,
contend with you, אך משפטים אדבר אותך, Ach mishpatim adaber otach, but
I have to speak like law and justice with you, מדוע דרך
רשעים צלחה, Madua derech reshaim tzalcha,
why God, is the path of the wicked, why is it successful?
שלו כל בגדי בגד, Shalu kol bogdei vaged, all of those who
rebel against you, why is it, why do they have it peaceful?
נטעתם גם שורשו, Netatam gam shorashu,
you have planted them and they've grown roots, ילכו גם עשו פרי,
Yelechu gam asu peri, they've gone and they've actually been fruitful, so
you know, why is all this fair? Right? This is what ירמיהו
Yirmiyahu is complaining to God, and ירמיהו Yirmiyahu of course prophesying on
the
destruction, you know, why
and the גמרא Gemara is reading this through the lens of what
it's just, because it just introduced נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar again. נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar, got
his strength when he came to דן. Dan.
So now we're moving from סנחריב and pointing backwards to אברהם Avraham
and סיסרא, Sisra, and now we're moving forward and pointing to the
ultimate destruction of, of נבוכדנצר, Nebuchadnezzar which is the ירמיהו Yirmiyahu context.
So ירמיהו Yirmiyahu is saying why, why is he successful? Okay, so
מה אהדרו ליה? Ma ahadru lei? What did they respond to him?
כי את רגלים רצתה וילאוך.
Ki
et raglim ratzta vayelauch.
This is in the same פסוק pasuk in ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu.
מה אהדרו ליה, Ma ahadru lei, who's the אהדרו? ahadru?
Sometimes the גמרא Gemara uses the plural when it's referring to the
heaven, meaning the, the angels, the divine retinue or whatever.
Okay. כי את רגלים רצתה וילאוך, Ki et raglim ratzta vayelauch, because
you have run against like foot, you know, racers, people of the,
are swift of the foot, and they have made you weary, ואיך
תתחרה את הסוסים? Veeich titchareh et hasusim? And how do you think
you can now compete against horses?
This reminds me of Michael Phelps and the shark.
ובארץ שלום אתה בוטח, Uve-eretz shalom atah voteiach, and you are confident
in, in a land of peace, ואיך תעשה בגאון הירדן? Veeich taaseh
bigon ha-Yarden? How do you think now you'll be able to compete
or you're able to be successful with the swelling of the Jordan?
So whoa, huh? What does all this mean? So משל לאדם אחד
שאמר, Mashal leadam echad sheamar, a person said, יכול אני לרוץ ג'
פרסאות לפני הסוסים, Yachol ani larutz gimmel parsaot lifnei hasusim, Ha! I
am so fast I can run three parsa'ing against horses, בין ביצי
המים, Bein bitzei hamayim, and not only that, I can do it
even like through a swamp, okay?
נזדמן לו רגלי אחד, Nizdamen lo ragli echad, so a certain like,
you know, foot racer or whatever, a certain like racer,
happens to bump into him. So said, oh, okay, let's, let's have
a little race, Mr.
Bigshot. רץ לפניו ג' מילין, Ratz lefanav gimmel milin, they ran not
three parsa'ing but three ג' מילין, gimmel milin, which is like a
quarter of the distance, ביבשה, Bayabasha, on nice dry land, ונלאה, Venila,
and the showoff, this loudmouth, grew weary, right? He lost the race.
אמר ליה, so the racer said to him, ומה לפני רגלי כך,
Umah lifnei ragli kach, if this is how you fare against, against
a person, לפני סוסים על אחת כמה וכמה, Lifnei susim al achat
kama vechama, how much more would you lose a race against horses?
ומה ג' מילין כך, Umah gimmel milin kach, you wearied after three
ג' מילין, gimmel milin, ג' פרסאות על אחת כמה וכמה, Gimmel parsaot
al achat kama vechama, how much more would you weary after, you
know, three ג' פרסאות? gimmel parsaot? ומה ביבשה כך, Umah bayabasha kach,
and if all this, how you perform on dry land, בין ביצי
המים על אחת כמה וכמה, Bein bitzei hamayim al achat kama vechama,
how much, how much worse would you do in a swamp? אף
אתה, Af atah, so now, how does, so how's this a response
to ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, which is saying why was נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar successful? Right?
Okay, that's a very nice little metaphor. What's the point? So
אף אתה ומה בשכר ד' פסיעות ששלמתי לו לאותו רשע שרץ אחר
כבודי. Af atah umah bishchar daled pesiot sheshilamti lo leoto rasha sheratz
achar kevodi. So why is נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar successful? God is going to
say him, I am paying him back for reward for the, for
the three, was it three or four? Four steps. Alright, I don't
know why we went from three to four. שדרך? Shadrach?
I don't know what to tell you. For the four steps, I
don't know why, for the four steps that he, that נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar
ran in my honor. Where did נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar run four steps in
God's honor? We're going to tell a story about that, okay? But
the story we're going to tell is that he ran four steps
to defend God's honor. And God said, and that's why I am
now giving him this reward, that he gets to be the king
that comes and destroys ירושלים, Yerushalayim, meaning it's not why ירושלים Yerushalayim
is being destroyed. ירושלים Yerushalayim is being destroyed due to the sins,
whatever. But someone had to do it, and here's why he's being
rewarded. Now, you're saying, but he's a רשע, rasha, why is this
for these four steps? It seems totally out of proportion. Don't worry.
Right. If that's what he gets for his four steps,
imagine what, you know, you and בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael or whatever
will get for all of their tremendous זכויות, zechuyot, and that's the
comparison to the guy who can't compete against the horses when, you
know, and so whatever, for even for such a tiny thing he's
going to get this, imagine what, you know, you'll get. Okay, so
yeah, we're going to, don't worry, I haven't forgotten about that. Okay,
so אז אתה תמהה, Az atah tamheh, you are astounded that he's
getting this reward? כשני משלם שכר לאברהם יצחק ויעקב, Kesheni meshalem sachar
le-Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov, when I finally get
around... When I finally get around to giving the reward to אברהם
יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov שרצו לפני כסוסים, sheratzu lefanai k'susim, they,
they ran in front of me like horses or whatever, they, they
did something really significant. על אחת כמה וכמה, al achas kamma v'kamma,
don't worry, you know, their reward is going to be so much
greater.
היינו דכתיב, hainu d'chsiv, ולנביאים נשבר לבי בקרבי, v'linviim nishbar libi b'kirbi,
for the prophets, which Rashi says here means אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham
Yitzchak v'Yaakov, you know, my heart was broken within me, meaning I
couldn't understand where is going to be the reward for, you know,
for, for אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov, for בני ישראל. Bnei
Yisrael. That's why my heart was
despondent. ורחפו כל עצמותי, v'rachafu kol atzmotai, הייתי כאיש שיכור, hayiti k'ish
shikkor, I was like, you know, my bones were weakened, I was
like a drunken man, drunken man. וכגבר עברו יין, v'kagever avru yayin,
and like a גבר, gever, a person עברו יין avru yayin that,
you know, had been drunk too much wine. מפני ה' ומפני דברי
קדשו, mipnei Hashem umipnei divrei kodsho, because of God and because of
God's holy words, meaning so, you know, I, maybe that's when maybe
the wine imagery is that therefore maybe it made me feel less
despondent or whatever because after God had explained it all to me.
Okay, anyway, so that's the context here, okay? נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar... is getting
rewarded because of the tiny little good deed he did. Don't worry,
that's just going to be a down payment or that's going to
be an indication of the tremendous reward you're going to receive in
the end. היינו דכתיב. hainu d'chsiv.
Okay, so now, הני ארבע פסיעות מאי? hani arba pisiot mai? What
are these four steps? So, דכתיב, d'chsiv, בעת היא שלח מרודך בלאדן
בן בלאדן מלך בבל ספרים. ba'eis hi shalach Merodach Baladan ben Baladan
Melech Bavel sefarim. At that time, מרודך בלאדן Merodach Baladan which could
be מרדוך, Marduk, which also could be, I think, it could just
be a name for king, okay, this king מרודך בלאדן Merodach Baladan
the son of בלאדן, Baladan, the מלך בבל, Melech Bavel, sent ספרים,
sefarim, sent, whatever, not books or whatever, letters or whatever it was,
scrolls. Anyway, when he heard that חזקיהו Chizkiyahu was healed from his
illness. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say: Big deal! So,
okay, some other king got better, that's what you're sending out, you
know, like messages to your kingdom? So the גמרא Gemara says, or
whatever, it's going to be a letter.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
משום דחלה חזקיהו ויחזק, mishum d'chala Chizkiyahu vayechazak, because חזקיהו Chizkiyahu got
sick and got better, שדר ליה ספרים ומנחה, shadar lei sefarim uminchah,
that's the end of the פסוק. posuk. He sent him like scrolls
and a, and a gift. Like, what, big deal? So the king
was sick and got better. So, so yes, in, because the end
of the פסוק posuk says, or another פסוק posuk in דברי הימים,
Divrei Hayamim, לדרוש המופת אשר היה בארץ, lidrosh hamofes asher haya ba'aretz,
because a wonder had been done in the land. What was the
wonder done when חזקיהו Chizkiyahu got better? So some king got better.
So דאמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, so now we're going to
explain it. אותו היום שמת בו אחז, oso hayom shemeis bo Achaz,
when אחז Achaz died, right, previous king, שתי שעות היה, shti sha'os
haya, the sun, it was only a two day, only there were
two hours of sunlight. Apparently, so because אחז Achaz was a wicked
king, God didn't want people to give him a eulogy or make
a big deal about the funeral, so God caused the sun to
set like twelve, ten hours ahead of its time, okay? It's the
day, it was only two hours of sunlight. וכי חלה חזקיהו, v'ki
chala Chizkiyahu, now when חזקיהו Chizkiyahu's grew sick, ואיספח, v'ispach, and then
he got better, הדרינו קודשא בריך הוא להנך עשר שעי, hadrinu Kudsha
Brich Hu l'hanach eser sha'ei, God made the day ten hours longer,
okay? It's like some type of a סימן siman that extending
חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu life. Because חזקיהו Chizkiyahu's was going to die, it says
התילה לנפשו למות, hatzeilah l'nafsho l'mus, and he prayed to God, he
turned his face to the wall or whatever, God extended his life.
So symbolically, also God made the...
Ten against the two and the ten?
Well, the ten is just based on a פסוק, posuk, but the
two hours? I don't, well, just because you have to do it
for the math, it's twelve minus ten. Okay, because...
and then חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu. father.
Oh right, I'm sorry, right, אחז Achaz was his father, correct. So
דכתיב, De-chtiv the reason we're getting this is because it's based on
a פסוק. posuk. הנני משיב צל המעלות אשר ירדה במעלות אחז, Hineni
meshiv tzel hama'alos asher yarda b'ma'alos Achaz, behold I will turn back
the shade of the, of the, what do you call it, the
sun clock that, you know, has now gone down
in, in
אחז's Achaz's sun clock, בשמש אחורנית עשר מעלות, bashemesh achornit eser ma'alos,
ten units. So it's explicit in the פסוק. posuk. God made the
sun return ten units, extended the day by ten hours. And because
it mentions אחז's Achaz's sun clock, we're going, in order to create
like, you know, it has to all balance out, we sort of
say, so for his father אחז, Achaz, who was a wicked king,
it set ten hours early, so for him it extended ten hours.
Okay, so,
okay, עשר מעלות. eser ma'alos. ותשב השמש עשר מעלות במעלות אשר ירדה,
vatishev hashemesh eser ma'alos b'ma'alos asher yorada, and the sun went back
ten, these ten gradations, ten
hours.
אמלי, amalei, so this connects with the earlier talk about the דעת,
da'as, the ignorant people and then the תורה? Torah?
I know, I'm getting back to that, we're finishing, I want to
finish this story and then go back to that
context between אחז Achaz and חזקיהו. Chizkiyah Yeah, yeah, oh, yeah.
Oh, you mean אחז Achaz was... פנים אמר? P'nim amar? Oh, because
he was the son of a wicked king and look what, oh,
that's interesting, that I hadn't seen. Okay, I'll get back to that.
Okay, so אמר ליה מאי האי? Amar Lei Mai Hai? So the
king of בבל, Bavel, this בלדן Baladan said, what's going on here?
The sun went, just the sun, the day extended ten hours? אמר
ליה חזקיהו חלש ואיתפח. Amar Lei Chizkiyah Chalash Ve'itpach. Oh, it's a
sign because the king חזקיהו was sick and got better. I don't
know how they found out so immediately. Anyway, אמר איכא גברא כי
האי ולא בעינא לשדורי ליה
שלמא? Amar Ika Gavra Ki Hai Velo Be'ina Leshadurei Lei Shalma? There's
a person like this and I should not have to go ask...
how could there be such a great king that the sun goes
back ten hours for him and I have not sent him, you
know, a welcome and a
greetings?
So כתבו ליה, Kitvu Lei, so write him, he said to his
scribes, write שלמא למלכא חזקיה, Shalma Lemalka Chizkiyah, peace to King חזקיה.
Chizkiyah. שלמא לקרתא דירושלם, Shalma Lekarta De'yerushalayim, peace to the city
Jerusalem. שלמא לאלהא רבא, Shalma Le'elaha Raba, peace to the great God.
נבוכדנצר... Nevuchadnetzar okay
now that was what the message he was going to send, this
בלדן. Baladan. נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar, who we know is going to be the,
you know, the king who is ultimately going to rise up. נבוכדנצר
ספרא דבלדן הוה. Nevuchadnetzar Safra De'baladan Hava. He was בלדן Baladan's scribe.
ההיא שעתא לא הוה התם. Hahi Sha'ata Lo Hava Hatam. That moment
when he assigned the scribes to write this letter, he wasn't there,
he had gone to the store on some, you know, on some
errand or something. Okay, כי אתא, Ki Ata, when he came back,
אמר להו היכי כתביתו? Amar Lehu Heichi Katvitu? He heard that they
had just sent a message to King חזקיה. Chizkiyah. He said, what
did you write in your message?
So אמרו ליה הכי כתבינן. Amru Lei Hachi Katvinan. Here's what we
wrote, where we just read a minute ago. אמר להו קריתו ליה
אלהא רבא? Amar Lehu Karitu Lei Elaha Raba? You called their God
the great God? וכתביתו ליה לבסוף? Vekatvitu Lei Levasof? And you wrote
God at the end? If you acknowledge he's a great God, he's
a great God before you talk about חזקיה. Chizkiyah. So אלא הכי
כתובו. Ela Hachi Kitvu. Here's what you should write. שלמא לאלהא רבא,
Shalma Le'elaha Raba, peace to the great God. שלמא לקרתא דירושלם, Shalma
Lekarta De'yerushalayim, peace to the city because even then God's city first.
God's city comes before חזקיה. Chizkiyah. And then שלמא למלכא חזקיה, Shalma
Lemalka Chizkiyah, peace to King חזקיה. Chizkiyah. Right, which is like the
religiously right thing to do but might not be the politically right
thing to do. You want to make a connection with an actual
king, you don't want to put him at the end. But he's
saying you got, if you really believe in his God, you have
to mention the God first. אמרו ליה קריינא דאיגרתא איהו ליהוי פרונקא.
Amru Lei Karyana De'igarta Ihu Leihavei Parvanka. The scribes said to him,
we saw this before, the great phrase in the גמרא. Gemara. The
one who reads the proclamation, the one who reads the letter, let
him be the one to execute it. Okay, ah, great idea. You
want to do that? You take care of it. Okay, so רהט
בתריה. Rahat Batrei. He ran after the messengers who were sent out
with this greetings, with this letter. כרהט ארבע פסיעות. Karahat Arba Pesiyot.
And he ran after to get the messenger. So after he had
ran four פסיעות, Pesiyot, four steps. Here's the four. By the way,
Michael, I just note here that in the side of the גמרא
Gemara it says and in the מדרש Midrash and in the ילקוט
Yalkut it says three steps. So that connects to the three before
by the whole thing about the three פרסאות. Parsa'ot. So there you
go. Anyway, this argues is four steps. אתא גבריאל ואוקמיה. Ata Gavriel
Ve'ukmei. So גבריאל, Gavriel,
who we've seen being playing a role on before, he came and
he stopped סנחריב from running more.
Me? I thought like ואוקמיה Ve'ukmei like he, you know, was making
him put him in front of where he needed to go. Oh,
probably the idea...
well we're going to see what that is... it is that idea
but I think אוקמיה Ukmei just means like he stopped him. אמר
רבי יוחנן אלמלא בא גבריאל והמידו. Amar Rabi Yochanan Ilmale Ba Gavriel
Ve'he'emido. If גבריאל Gavriel had not come and stopped him after the
four steps, לא הוה תקנה לשונאיהם של ישראל, Lo Hava Takana Lesonayehem
Shel Yisrael, because he's being rewarded for these steps. If he would
have had the opportunity to run a mile to catch up to
the guy, then you know, what would have happened to שונאיהם של
ישראל Sonayehem Shel Yisrael is a euphemism whatever, whatever happened to his
ability to wipe out Israel? Okay, כי הוי כתבי. Ki Havei Katvi.
Now,
so that's his four steps. Okay, now before we go on, first
of all, I just got to tell you this story. It's a
little tangential but it made an impression on me. Yesterday I happened
to be in the city and you know, I was buying a
fruit from these fruit stands, whatever on the sidewalk and it always
impressed me how like honest these guys are. You know, you see
how super careful they are about, you know, and like if it's
a little bit extra they throw in, and you could say they're
just doing it for business, you know, they want to show that
they're honest so people come to them. Anyway, I bought some stuff
from him and he did the math, whatever, you know, he counted
in whatever language he was counting, I wasn't following, he said 12
dollars. Fine, I trust him, I give him 12 dollars. I'm walking
away, I'm looking in my bag and just doing the חשבון Cheshbon
in my head and I'm saying, oh wait, seems like it should
be 11.50, well maybe this thing cost 2.50 instead of 2.00 dollars.
I was a block and a half away. He comes running after
me and he says, here is your 50 cents. So it's like,
it's like stories they tell about the חפץ חיים. Chafetz Chaim. So
it's like I was just so impressed by that. So anyway, all
right. Anyway, what does this have to do with the, with the,
what do you call it, with the בני עם הארץ? Bnei Am
Ha'aretz? So David mentioned, I didn't even see this, you know, it's
an indication, look you know, חזקיה Chizkiyah was a son of a
wicked person and look what happened to him, so it's like a
symbol of בני עם הארץ. Bnei Am Ha'aretz. רש״י Rashi says no,
רש״י Rashi says the point is is that the reason the גמרא
Gemara is going to say later בני עם הארץ, Bnei Am Ha'aretz,
we didn't get to it, but it's going to say because the
descendants of like סנחריב are sitting in the בית מדרש Beit Medrash
and the descendants of המן Haman are sitting in the בית מדרש,
Beit Medrash, etc. etc. and that's why, you know, even though they
come from the עם הארץ. Am Ha'aretz. Now what, what רש״י, Rashi,
but the way רש״י Rashi reads it is, when you give honor
to
the
בני עם הארץ... Bnei Am Ha'aretz... the reason they're getting their honor
is not because of what their fathers were, you know, because even
the fathers of really even really wicked fathers, you know, סנחריב *Sancheriv*
and המן Haman, *Haman* and all these people, it's to let them
know it's because of the Torah and it's not because like of
the honor of their fathers. So that's sort of the way that
like רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, you know, connects it. It's a pretty weak
connection. I did want to tell you what the מהרש"א *Maharsha* said,
because the מהרש"א *Maharsha* should have made a I'm trying to now
I'm trying to remember what the מהרש"א *Maharsha*'s point was that I
think the be careful not once they're already תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei Chachamim*
give them כבוד *kavod* but let them know where the כבוד *kavod*
is coming from. The מהרש"א *Maharsha* says what I think is better
more פשט *pshat*, like you should make careful to not be sort
of ties into the statement before, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
before about like holding Torah from a kid and not thinking oh
he can't learn, why should I bother teaching him Torah? Remember that
earlier אגדתא agadata *aggadata*? I don't know if you remember that. So
the מהרש"א *Maharsha* said, the מהרש"א *Maharsha* should have read that into
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So the מהרש"א *Maharsha* says here as well,
don't say like why should I teach these people? They're living they're
growing up in these bad homes, they're under all these bad influences,
my Torah is not going to do any good to them, right?
So no, you should know that they can be influenced not just
by their home but they can be influenced by their teachers as
well. And therefore don't give up on them. And the evidence is,
you know, that the בני *Bnei*, these children of סנחריב *Sancheriv*, the
children of רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* according to you, right I mean
that's a point, חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu* the child of אחז *Achaz*, so that
is like why you should not give up on these kids. So
it's a I think it's a nicer message than רש"י Rashi *Rashi*.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is if they become תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei Chachamim* give
them honor, but let them know we're not honoring them for their
father. You know, or maybe another way is like anyway fine, but
the מהרש"א *Maharsha* says don't give up on them before you educate
them, understand your responsibility to educate them because you can influence them
and you can make them into צדיקים *tzaddikim*.
The first two parts had nothing to do with it, just
because there are three first two parts we just had a yeah,
we just had to get to this whole sort of story at
the end. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* continues.
We already read and all that, that's what I meant.
Exactly, yeah, that was just I don't know somehow wrapped in. So
now the גמרא *Gemara* continues. אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rebbe Yochanan*. Okay
we just did that one. Okay. מאי בלאדן בן בלאדן *Mai Baladan
ben Baladan*? Why does he have the same name as his father?
Like what, was he ספרדי *Sefardi* or something? So
but the גמרא *Gemara* says it's a little unusual for a son
to have the same name as the father. So מאי בלאדן בן
בלאדן *Mai Baladan ben Baladan*? אמר בלאדן מלכא הוה *Amar Baladan Malka
hava*. בלאדן *Baladan* was a king and his father ואשתני אפיה והוה
ככלבא *v'ishtanei apay ve'hava ke'kalba*. And his face changed and it looked
like a dog. Now that's a very strange claim to be making.
Panzino says that apparently there are statues of this king that actually
still exist have the king and have his whatever people, there are
always dogs in the statues. So he says maybe that's where the
גמרא *Gemara* got this idea to associate him with dogs. Okay. היינו
דכתיב hayinu dichtsiv, *Hainu dechsiv*, that's what's meant by, excuse me one
minute, היינו דכתיב *Hainu dechsiv*, והוה יתיב בריה על מלכותיה *vehava yasiv
brei al malchuso*. So the son took over his kingship now that
the father is looking like a dog. כי הוה כתיב *Ki hava
kasiv*, הוה כתיב שמיה ושמיה דאבוה *hava kasiv shemei u'shemei de'avuha*. So
when he would write himself, he gave himself his father's name and
he would say בלאדן *Baladan* the son of בלאדן *Baladan*, you know,
in order to give honor to his father, as if his father
was still the king because you know his father was still around,
it's just whatever, his father couldn't couldn't sort of serve in his
office right now. היינו דכתיב *Hainu dechsiv*, and that was a fulfillment
of the verse, בן יכבד אב ועבד אדניו *ben yechabeid av v'eved
adonav*. A son will give honor to the father and a slave
to the master. בן יכבד אב הא דאמרן *ben yechabeid av hada
de'amaran*, that's what we said, that he's basically didn't, you know, took
his father's name and attributed himself to his father, a continuation of
his father. ועבד אדניו דכתיב *v'eved adonav dechsiv*, ובחדש החמישי בעשור לחדש
*u'vachodesh hachamishi b'asor lachodesh*, on the fifth month and the tenth of
the month, בשנת תשע עשרה שנה למלך נבוכדנאצר Nevuchadnezzar מלך בבל Bavel
*bishnas tsha esrei shana l'melech Nevuchadnezzar melech Bavel*, the nineteenth year of
the king נבוכדנאצר Nevuchadnezzar *Nebuchadnezzar* the king of בבל Bavel *Bavel*, בא
נבוזראדן Nevuzaradan, רב טבחים *ba Nevuzaradan rav tabachim*, נבוזראדן Nevuzaradan, *Nevuzaradan* the
head slaughterer or like the head general came, לפני מלך בבל Bavel
בירושלים *lifnei melech Bavel b'Yerushalayim*, in front of the king of בבל
*Bavel* in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, and he is going to now obviously,
you know, fight the war and destroy the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash.
*Beis Hamikdash*. וישרף את בית ה' ואת בית המלך *Vayisrof es beis
Hashem ve'es beis hamelech*, and he burnt down the house of God
and the house of the king of Israel, not נבוכדנאצר Nevuchadnezzar *Nebuchadnezzar*.
Okay. So the point basically being that he went and he made
it appear before נבוכדנאצר Nevuchadnezzar *Nebuchadnezzar*. Now so that's a slave or
a servant respecting the master. Now that doesn't show much respect, you
know, you come and your you know the king is there, you
appear before the king. So now let's take a look. ומי סליק
נבוכדנאצר Nevuchadnezzar לירושלים *U'mi salik Nevuchadnezzar l'Yerushalayim*? But wait a minute, since
when was נבוכדנאצר *Nebuchadnezzar* in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*? So this is now
going to clarify the point. והא כתיב ויעלו אתו אל מלך בבל
רבלתה *Veha ksiv v'ayu oso el melech Bavel l'Rivlasa*, they brought him,
צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*, when they captured him, to the king of בבל *Bavel*
to רבלתה *Rivlah*. ואמר v'amar רבי אבהו זו אנטוכיא *Ve'amar Rebbe Abahu
zu Antuchia*, this is אנטוכיא *Antioch*, which is not in the land
of Israel. So when if so clearly the king of בבל *Bavel*
was out of Israel. So what does it mean that when נבוזראדן
Nevuzaradan, *Nevuzaradan* came he appeared before the king of בבל *Bavel*? רב
חסדא ורבי יצחק בר אבדימי *Rav Chisda ve'Rebbe Yitzchak bar Avdimi*, חד
אמר דמות דיוקנו היתה חקוקה *chad amar dmus dyukno hayesa chakuka*. and
his whole chariot. So what it means he appeared before Nebuchadnezzar doesn't
mean Nebuchadnezzar was literally in the land of Israel, but he made
it as if Nebuchadnezzar was with him in Israel. He engraved the
image of Nebuchadnezzar on his chariot. The word דיוקנו is the same
word as icon. Okay, he engraved the image of Nebuchadnezzar onto his
chariot. וחד אמר, vechad amar, אימתיה יתירה היתה לו ממנו, eimateih yetirah
hayetah lo mimeno, Nebuzaradan had such tremendous fear of Nebuchadnezzar or awe,
ודומה כמי שעומד לפניו, v'domeh k'mi she'omed lefanav, wherever he would go,
he would be feeling the presence of Nebuchadnezzar. You know how some
people talk about that, like you know, I always feel my father's
presence, you know, or whatever, in front of me, like what would
he say if I were to like do something wrong, if I
would whatever. So he always sensed the presence of Nebuchadnezzar there. So
that's the sense of a servant honoring a master, okay, either by
an external show of honor, engraving the image on his chariot, or
by internalizing that constant sense of his master being present. Okay. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, טעין תלת מאה קודנייתא, t'ein t'las me'ah kudnayasa, now
that we've introduced, sort of we circled back to Nebuchadnezzar, right? So
we talked about the whole Sennacherib, etc., but then we pointed to
Nebuchadnezzar got his strength when he came to Dan. You know, why
did he get this strength for these four steps? That's why he's
getting the power. So we're basically focused now on Nebuchadnezzar, right, and
Nebuzaradan, who came to fight, had the image of Nebuchadnezzar. So we're
now moving to this battle against Jerusalem, okay, and then we're going
to focus on that. Some of this is parallel, some stories in
גיטין, Gittin, which are the famous אגדתא about the destruction of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, טעין תלת מאה קודנייתא, t'ein t'las me'ah
kudnayasa, the burden of 300 mules, נרגא
דפרזלא, narga d'parzla, so
of iron, not iron, פרזלא parzla is
what?
Yeah, iron. It is iron. All right, of iron hammers
דשלטי
בפרזלא, d'shalt b'parzla,
they're so sharp that they're
iron hammers
that can break through
iron,
שדריה
נבוכדנצר
לנבוזראדן. shad'reih Nebuchadnezzar l'Nebuzaradan.
So
he sent
in
these armaments to go and destroy ירושלים. Yerushalayim, He sent them 300
wagons or mules beladen with these iron hammers that
can
break
through
iron
doors.
כולהו בלעו בחדא דשא
דירושלים. kulyahu balyu b'chada dasha d'Yerushalayim.
They were all destroyed trying to break through one door of one
of the doors of Jerusalem.
כנאמר, k'ne'emar, פתחיה יחד
בכשיל וכילפות יהלומון, p'sachah yachad b'khishil v'kheyalfos yahalomun,
right, its opening together they will sort of with the hammer and
will grow weary and so on. So basically they even using all
of this armament, all of this weaponry against ירושלים, they didn't get
even through one door. So בעי למיהדר, v'ayeil m'hadar, so Nebuzaradan said,
"All right, that's it, I'm going back." So אמר, מסתפינא דלא ליעבדו
בי כהיכא דעבדו בסנחריב. mistafina d'la l'avdu bi k'heicha d'avdu b'Sancheiriv. So
then he said, now does this mean Nebuzaradan wanted to go back
but said to himself, or does this mean Nebuzaradan wanted to go
back but Nebuchadnezzar said to him, "No, we can't retreat because I,
Nebuchadnezzar, am afraid that they'll do to me what they did to
Sennacherib." It wasn't clear exactly who's afraid, is Nebuchadnezzar afraid or Nebuzaradan?
How do they translate it in the English?
See it has
in
parentheses, Nebuzaradan sought to withdraw. Yeah, then they have, "He said."
He said, Nebuzaradan said. Right. So it's not exactly clear. It could
be Nebuzaradan said this, it could be Nebuchadnezzar, but presumably it's Nebuzaradan.
I would like to go back but I can't because I'm afraid
that then my kids will kill me because it'll be an embarrassment.
So okay.
So נפק קלא, n'phek kahlah, some voice came out, a heavenly voice
or something, ואמר and said to him, שבר בר שבר, sh'var bar
sh'var, jumper the son of a jumper. What does it mean a
jumper? Might have to do with the way that Nebuchadnezzar tried to
run after the messenger, the story from before.
Leper or leaper?
Oh, I'm sorry, leaper.
I know. Right.
Okay, so נבוזראדן שבר, Nebuzaradan sh'var, jump, מטא זימנא, m'to zimna,
here's your leap of faith. The time has come, דמקדשא דיחרב, d'mikdash
d'yechariv, even at what was the point of the 300 hammers? I
guess to point out that like without God's permission they couldn't have
done anything. But now God is saying now the time has come
for Jerusalem to be destroyed, I mean the Temple to be destroyed,
והיכלא דייקלי v'heichala d'yikli and the היכל heichal to be burnt up
in fire. פשיא חד נרגא, pashya chad narga, he was left with
one hammer. Okay. אתא מחא בקופא, ata machi b'kupah, he banged against
the door with the back of the hammer, not even the sharp
point, ואיפתח v'iftach and it opened. So when God wanted it, it
all happened because God wanted it to happen. כנאמר... k'ne'emar... It was
known like the one who brings like in the forest, hammers
against the trees of the forest. All right, so God knows or
whatever it was with God's permission. הוי קטיל ואזיל, Havei katil ve'azil,
so then he was slaughtering the people of the city עד דמטא
להיכלא ad demata leheichala until he came to the היכל, Heichal, to
the temple. אידליק ביה נורא, Idlik bei nura, he lit it on
fire. גבה
היכלא,
Gvah
heichala, so and like, on top of the היכל, Heichal, and the
fire rose up, and it was rising up to heaven. דרכו ביה
מן שמיא, Darchu bei min shamaya, so in heaven they trampled down
the
fire, like God didn't want it to symbolize, like you wouldn't want
it to be sending, be symbolic of an idea like they were
destroying the God, our
God, right? They're burning the היכל, Heichal, the fires are going up
to heaven, so from heaven it was like it pushed down the
flames. So it was very clear that it was like a this-worldly
destruction of the
temple, not an other-worldly destruction. Okay. So דרכו ביה מן שמיא, Darchu
bei min shamaya, from up on high they trampled down the flames.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, גת דרך ה' לבתולת בת יהודה, Gat darach Hashem livtulat
bat Yehuda, something that's normally about the destruction, God has trampled us
like in a pressing, like an olive press or like a wine
press,
anyway here like trampling of the grapes, but here it is saying
that he kept the flames down. Okay.
כד חזא דאתאי, Kad chaza de'atai, now when נבוזראדן Nevuzaradan
now started feeling very haughty. Look at this, I've now destroyed their
city, destroyed their temple.
נפק בת קול ואמרה, Nafak bat kol ve'amra, a heavenly voice came
out and said to him, because he should have got the message
from the fact of how hard it was to get in in
the first place, so a heavenly voice came out and said to
him, עמא קטילא קטלת, Ama ketila katalt, don't think you're such a
big shot.
You've killed a nation that was already killed, meaning I have already
decreed upon them. You're just actualizing what already was going to happen
because I, God, had decreed, which was of course the point of
the beginning of the story. So don't take any credit for this.
Okay. היכלא קליא קלית, Heichala kalya kalit, a already burned temple, you
were burning something that was already burned. קימחא טחינא טחינת, Kimcha techina
techinat, you're just grinding stuff that's already flour. Don't think you're grinding
wheat, it was already flour. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says, קחי רחים
וטחני קמח. Kechi rechain utchaini kemach. Now this is a verse that's
about going into exile. Take a millstone or take a mill וטחני
קמח utchaini kemach and grind flour. It doesn't say grind wheat, it
says grind flour. That's like that old joke, what do you put
in a toaster? Toast. No, you put bread in the toaster. Okay.
So you don't grind flour, you grind wheat. Anyway, but here it
says, prophesying about the exile, take a mill and grind flour. Of
course it means you grind it into flour, but okay.
גלי צמתך, Gali tzamtech, reveal your temples, like the hair of your
temples. חשפי שובל, Chasfi shoveil, reveal your legs.
I'm sorry, Rashi says שובל shoveil is
the part in your hair, I guess. גלי שוק, Gali shok, uncover
your calf. עברי נהרות, Ivri neharot, pass through the rivers. Okay, so
anyway, and go into exile. חיטים לא נאמר, Chitim lo ne'emar, it
doesn't say wheat אלא
קמח, ela kemach, grind something that's already flour. So נבוזראדן, Nevuzaradan this
was already happening. In my eyes it had already happened, you're just
actualizing it. Okay. Now חזא דמיה דזכריה, Chaza dmyei deZecharya, he saw
the blood of זכריה, Zecharya, who was a prophet. There's a זכריה
Zecharya who was at the beginning of the בית שני, Bayit Sheni,
but this was a prophet towards the end of the בית ראשון.
Bayit Rishon. This is a very famous story, we even have it
retold in the קינות Kinot of תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. He saw
the blood of זכריה, Zecharya, who זכריה Zecharya was telling them to
do תשובה teshuva and that they were going to be destroyed or
whatever, and basically it says that they stoned him in the temple
court, in the temple, in the בית המקדש. So he saw there
the blood of זכריה Zecharya דהוה קא רתח, dehava ka ratach, it
was still boiling. אמר
להו, Amar lehu, he said to the people around him, to the
Jews, מאי האי, Mai hai, what is this? אמרו ליה, Amru leh,
דם זבחים הוא Dam zvachim hu דאשתפיך, de'ishtapich, it's blood of
sacrifices that was spilled. אמר להו, Amar lehu, אייתי ואנסי, Aiti ve'ansi,
go bring me an animal and let's test it אי מידמו ei
midmu if it's comparable to the blood of animals. אייתי, he slaughtered
an animal ולא אידמו, velo idmu, it didn't look like it. So
he says, clearly this is not animal blood. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
גלו לי, Galu li, tell me ואם לאו, ve'im lav, if you
don't tell me what this is really about, סריקנא לכו לבשרייכו, sarikna
lechu levasraichu, I will flay your skin off of you במסרקי דפרזלא
bemasrakei deparzla with an iron comb. אמרו ליה, Amru leh, they said
to him, האי כהן ונביא הוא. Hai kohen veNavi hu. Okay fine,
this was a person who was both a כהן kohen and a
נביא, navi, a very holy man, דאיתנבי להו לישראל בחורבנא דירושלים, de'itnabi
lehu l'Yisrael bechurbana deYerushalayim,
he prophesied against Israel about the destruction of Jerusalem וקטלוהו vekatlohu and
they killed him. They didn't want to hear it. אמר להו, אנא
מפייסנא ליה, Ana mefayisne leh, I will appease him. אייתי רבנן, Aiti
rabbanan, he took the Rabbis
וקטיל עלויה, vekatil alavyei, of course, a little retro-projecting that there was
Rabbis at that time, anyway, he slaughtered the Rabbis on top of
it, like the righteous are going to die and that will somehow
be an atonement for the sin, maybe because they also were the
heads and therefore they were responsible. Okay. ולא נח, Velo nach, the
blood did not stop. boiling.
אייתי דרדקי דבי
רב,
Aiti dardeki
de-bei
Rav, he took the school children. So obviously they're not responsible, but
they're the innocent ones, so here is blood of an innocent, so
let's take the blood of innocents and maybe somehow that will atone.
I'm not sure exactly how two wrongs make a right. But anyway,
קטלינהו, katlinhu,
he slaughtered them over the blood, ולא נח, velo nach, the blood
did not stop boiling. אייתי פרחי כהונה, Aiti pirchei kehuna, he took
the young Kohanim. קטלינהו, katlinhu, slaughtered, ולא נח, velo nach,
it didn't stop boiling. עד דקטלינהו תשעים וארבע ריבוא, Ad dikatlinhu tishim
ve-arba'in ribo,
94 myriads, 940,000 people he slaughtered, ולא
נח, velo nach, and it didn't stop boiling. קרב לגבי, Karav legabei,
אמר,
so he approached the blood, אמר, and he said, זכריה זכריה טובים
שבהן איבדתי, Zecharia Zecharia tovim shebahen ibadeti, I've now destroyed the best,
the cream of the crop, 940,000, ניחא לך דאקטלינהו לכולהו? nicha lach
de-aktilinnhu lechulhu? Do
you want me to kill them all out? מיד נח, Miyad nach,
immediately it stopped boiling. He should have said that a while earlier,
but anyway, הרהר תשובה בדעתיה, hirher teshuva bedatei, so
he finally now he's realizing this is all about God and doing
God's will, so he finally had a thought of doing תשובה. teshuva.
אמר מה הם שלא איבדו אלא נפש אחת, Amar mah hem she-lo
ibdu ela nefesh achas, the people here they only killed one innocent
person, זכריה, Zecharia, כך, kach, and look at how God demanded justice
for that one
person, ההוא גברא, this person, meaning me, מה תהא עליה, mah tehei
alei, what will be my fate? I have actually now killed in
my attempt to find vengeance, look at all the innocents I killed.
אזל שדר פרטיטא לביתיה, Azal shadar priteita leveiteih, he ran away, he
sent
a
instructions to his house, like a final testament, ואיגייר, ve-isgayar, and he
converted. Okay, so now we have נבוזראדן, the destroyer
of Jerusalem and the killer of tens of thousands, according to the
גמרא hundreds of thousands, of the Jewish people, and now he's doing
תשובה teshuva and we accepted him. Okay, which is actually there's an
interesting תשובה teshuva about תשובה, teshuva, Responsum, after the Holocaust by Rav
Oshry about a Nazi who wanted to convert. Somebody who had been
a Nazi after the war who wanted to convert, right? So could
you imagine such a thing? So here the גמרא actually has a
story like that. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
I don't remember in the end what the answer was, I really
have to look at that תשובה, teshuva, that would be such an
appropriate תשובה teshuva in the context of this גמרא, right? תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, נעמן, Na'aman, now they're talking about wicked people who converted,
although נעמן Na'aman wasn't
wicked, נעמן גר תושב היה, Na'aman ger toshav hayah, remembers about נעמן,
Na'aman, he got healed from his leprosy, he, but he stayed, he
didn't become part of the Jewish people, he worshipped God but he
was a גר תושב, ger toshav, he was a non-Jew who worshipped
God.
נבוזראדן, but נבוזראדן גר צדק היה, Nevuzaradan ger tzedek hayah, according to
this story, he became a righteous convert, he became a Jew. מבני
בניו של סיסרא, mibnei banav shel Sisra,
now this also ties back to the story about children of עמי
הארץ, amei ha'aretz, be careful with them, because the great-great-grandkids of סיסרא,
Sisra, למדו תורה בירושלים, limdu torah biyerushalayim, they taught Torah in ירושלים,
מבני בניו של סנחריב למדו תורה ברבים, mibnei banav shel Sancheriv limdu
torah berabbim, and the descendants of סנחריב, because סיסרא Sisra and
סנחריב didn't really succeed, they went to war but they didn't really
succeed, they taught Torah to the masses, ומאן נינהו? u-man ninhu? Who
are they? שמעיה ואבטליון, Shemaya ve-Avtalyon, שמעיה ואבטליון, Shemaya ve-Avtalyon, they succeeded
in teaching Torah to the masses. So you see, no matter which
family you come from, the descendants can turn out to be great
people. מבני בניו של המן למדו תורה בבני ברק, mibnei banav shel
Haman limdu torah bivnei brak, and the descendants of
המן, they taught Torah in בני ברק. Bnei Brak. ואף מבני בניו
של אותו רשע, ve-af mibnei banav shel oso rasha, now even the
descendants of that wicked person, now that's נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar ביקש הקדוש ברוך
הוא להכניסן תחת כנפי השכינה, bikesh hakadosh baruch hu lehachnisan tachas kanfei
hashchina, God wanted to accept them. So it doesn't say that נבוכדנצר
Nevuchadnezzar, did תשובה, teshuva, but basically his grandkids maybe wanted to convert
and God wanted to convert them. אמרו מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך
הוא, Amru malachei hashareis lifnei hakadosh baruch hu, so the angels said,
ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, מי שהחריב את ביתך ושרף את
היכלך תכניס אתה תחת כנפי השכינה? mi she-hechriv es beischa ve-saraf es
heichalecha tachnis attah tachas kanfei hashchina? The one who destroyed your house
and you'll bring them under your heavenly wings? So היינו דכתיב, that's
what's meant, רפאנו את בבל ולא נרפתה, ripeinu es bavel velo nispasa,
I wanted to heal בבל but it wasn't healed because basically the
angels didn't let me accept him in. Now of course, this is
very strange because we
won't accept him or God didn't accept him, I mean, what does
it mean God didn't? Did the people accept but God didn't accept?
Like did they convert but God didn't accept the conversion?
But anyway, God is not accepting the descendants of נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar but
נבוזראדן himself who was the actual person who wiped it out, he
was accepted. So it's like the guy who actually did, but okay,
it's I guess the difference between the guy who was just following
orders, although based on this story, he wasn't just following orders,
he got carried away. but as opposed to the king that actually
was making it all happen, right? So it's but it's really fascinating
in terms of thinking about that, like who do we accept in
after they've done terrible things? But it sounds like they wouldn't even
accept in his kids, which is particularly surprising, his grandkids, right? Okay.
Okay.
Now, עולא אמר Ulla amar Ulla said, זה נבוכדנאצר. ze Nevuchadnezzar. Oh
so I'm sorry we just that's the end of it. That's נבוכדנאצר
that he wanted he or his kids wanted to come in and
God wouldn't let it. Okay, רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר Rabbi Shmuel
bar Nachmani amar no no no, the בבל that wanted to be
healed but wasn't healed is אלו נהרות בבל elu naharot Bavel the
rivers of בבל which are bitter and they were never and you
know the water remained bitter. ותרגומא דציננא דבבלאי ve'targuma d'tzinana d'Bavlai
and תנא Tanna this is like bitter palm trees that grow by
the river. Okay, אמר עולא. Amar Ulla. עמון ומואב. Ammon u'Moav. Okay,
so now we're moving on. Okay, so that was נבוכדנאצר and נבוזראדן
but like it's not like you know there could still be some
good that comes even out of the most evil people. Now, עמון
ומואב Ammon u'Moav שכני רעים לירושלים הוו shcheinei ra'im l'Yerushalayim havu they
were bad neighbors of Jerusalem. כיוון דשמעינהו לנביאי דקא מיתנבו לחורבנא דירושלים
keivan d'sham'inhu l'nevi'ei d'ka mitnabu l'churbana d'Yerushalayim
they heard the prophets prophesying the destruction of
Jerusalem, so they figured hey let's make this happen. שלחו לנבוכדנאצר פוק
ותא Shalchu l'Nevuchadnezzar puk v'ta they sent to נבוכדנאצר come come it's
an opportunity for you to wipe out Jerusalem. Okay, אמר מסתפינא דלא
ליעבדו בי כי היכי דעבדו בקמאי Amar mistafina d'la l'yavdu bi ki
heichi d'avdu b'kama'ei
I'm afraid they're going to do to me what they did to
the earlier ones, like what happened when סנחריב tried, you know, we
just mentioned סנחריב and סיסרא, Sisera, you know, and whatever so all
these people attempted and anyway but סנחריב particularly. שלחו ליה כי אין
האיש בביתו Shalchu lei ki ein ha'ish b'veito
don't worry, God's not home anymore. הלך בדרך מרחוק halach b'derech merachok
he's on a long way journey. You know God's abandoned the people
at this stage, that was earlier stage this stage God's abandoned the
people. Okay this is פסוקים psukim in משלי. Mishlei. ואין איש אלא
הקדוש ברוך הוא V'ein ish ela haKadosh Baruch Hu man that means
God, שנאמר ה' איש מלחמה. shene'emar Hashem ish milchama. שלח להו בקריבא
הוא Shalach lehu b'keriva hu
so all right God maybe is not immediately there but He's nearby.
God will come back to them when they're in trouble. ותו שלחו
ליה V'tu shalchu lei and they sent to him again quoting the
פסוק, pasuk, הלך
בדרך מרחוק halach b'derech merachok no
he's on a long way journey he ain't coming back. שלח להו
אית להו צדיקי דבעי רחמי ומייתי ליה Shalach lehu it lehu tzaddikei
d'ba'ei rachamei u'maiti lei
but there's still righteous people, they'll cry out to God and God
will return. שלחו ליה Shalchu lei they sent to him again quoting
the פסוק pasuk צרור הכסף לקח בידו tzror hakesef lakach b'yado no
he's took his money with him he ain't coming back. ואין כסף
אלא צדיקים V'ein kesef ela tzaddikim and כסף kesef means the righteous,
שנאמר ואכרה לי בחמישה עשר כסף shene'emar va'ekreha li b'chamisha asar kesef
I dug for her, I purchased from her with 15 you know
coins of silver, רש"י says 15 is the 15th of ניסן Nissan
means it's referring to the to the redemption from מצרים, Mitzrayim, וחומר
שעורים ולתך שעורים v'chomer se'orim v'letech se'orim
with this these units of barley, anyway somehow it means for the
because of the merits of the righteous they were redeemed from Egypt.
Okay, so they said don't worry he says the righteous have all
left also, everybody's abandoned all the worthwhile people have abandoned. שלח להו
הדרי בתיובתא Shalach lehu hadri b'tiyuvta oh
you know they might be all wicked now but they'll see me
coming they'll all do תשובה teshuva ובעי רחמי ומייתי ליה u'ba'ei rachamei
u'maiti lei and they'll and they'll pray to God and they'll bring
God back. שלחו ליה כבר קבע להו זמן Shalchu lei kvar kava
lehu zman
no He has set a time for when you know the time
has come to destroy Jerusalem like we saw by the earlier story.
Don't worry it's
happening. שנאמר ליום הכסא יבוא לביתו Shene'emar l'yom hakisei yavo l'veito ואין
כסא אלא זמן v'ein kisei ela zman and that is that means
a time שנאמר בכסה ליום חגנו. shene'emar bakese l'yom chagenu. Oh so
I guess this means not just that He set a time to
destroy Jerusalem, yeah
רש"י says He set a time until He's coming back. He's not
coming back because it fits with the whole image that He's left
and He's taken His money. He set a time that He's not
coming back until 70 years from the destruction of the Temple. So
don't worry. He will come back but not for the next immediate
future, for now He's totally left the house and now is your
time to come and destroy. Okay? He's not coming back for 70
years. שלח להו סיתוא הוא Shalach lehu sitva hu ah you know
it's the fall, it's getting to be the winter, ורמיא טינא דאתי
איטלטל ממיטרא v'ramia tina d'ati etaltal m'mitra the snow and the rain.
Sounds like a little wimp. But the point is is that he's
trying to get any excuse that it's so interesting. Right? A minute
ago we said like maybe this is also trying to say why
you know there was some merit even in נבוכדנאצר or נבוכדנאצר's kids.
Like he was reluctant. In the end he did it but he
was reluctant, right?
And it was in טבת Teves when he when he began the
siege. What?
They
say that the siege began in טבת Teves which was winter.
In טבת, Teves, right, that's true too, עשרה בטבת, Asara b'Teves, right.
שלחו ליה Shalchu lei that's a good point. שלחו ליה Shalchu lei
they sent him תא שינא דטורא ta shina d'tura no come by
the way of the mountains, the mountains will protect you from the
elements. שנאמר שלחו כר Shene'emar shalchu char they sent a messenger מושל
ארץ moshel eretz to the to the king of to the ruler
of the land מסלע מדברה misela midbara to come through the מדבר
midbar through the rock. to the mountains. אל הר בת ציון El
har bat tziyon to the mountain of Zion. שלחו ליה Shalchu leh
but he sent to them, אי אתינא לית לי דוכתא דיתבינא בה
Ee asina leit li dukhta di asvina beh that if I come
then I will have nowhere to place my troops. שלחו ליה Shalchu
leh they sent him
קברות שלהם מעולים מפלטין שלך. Kivros shelahem me'ulim mi-paltrin shelcha. Their graveyards
are better than your palace. Of course within this, like you're saying
come destroy it, there's also sort of saying like, you know, acknowledgment,
oh, but you know, really it's at a much higher level than
you. But of course what it could also be reading is there's
more room in their graveyards than in your palace. Why is there
more room? Because as רש"י says the graves are in the caves.
They buried in the caves. So they have all these caves and
you can put up your men in the caves. Okay. דכתיב בעת
ההיא נאם השם יוציאו את עצמות מלכי יהודה ואת עצמות שריו ואת
עצמות הכהנים, Ba-et ha-hi ne'um Hashem yotziu et atzmot malchei yehuda ve'et
atzmot sarav ve'et atzmot hakohanim, they'll take all these bones out of
the graves ואת עצמות הנביאים ve'et atzmot hanevi'im the bones of the
prophets and of the kings and of whatever of the כהנים kohanim
ואת עצמות יושבי ירושלים מקבריהם ve'et atzmot yoshvei yerushalayim mikivreihem they'll take
them from their graves ושטחום לשמש ולירח ולכל צבא השמים ushetachum lashemesh
velayarei'ach ulechol tzeva hashamayim they'll spread them out to the sun and
the moon and all the stars אשר אהבום asher ahevum they've loved,
they loved the sun and the moon and the stars, you know,
they've worshiped them. So their bones are going to be spread out
up to the heavens ואשר עבדום va'asher avadum and they worshiped them
ואשר הלכו אחריהם. va'asher halchu achareihem. So the point is, why are
they taking out the bones? Because נבוכדנצר is quartering his troops in
the caves, so they're emptying the caves of all the bones so
that they can be quartered in it. Okay. And we'll end here
and continue with this tomorrow.